# James Umogu

3-11267 133 Street, Surrey BC V3R 0E3 +1 236 512 5912 oviejames@yahoo.com linkedin.com/in/jamesumogu

# Data Analyst - Business Analyst - Enterprise/Data Architect

Senior data analyst, data manager and project manager with career spanning 20+ years, seeking opportunity to improve data/business analysis effectiveness in your organization. I have experience in development, implementation, and oversight of data governance frameworks. My extensive and in-depth knowledge of data management and business analysis, acquired over the past 16 years, combined with my project management proficiency will contribute to significant improvement of your organizational efficiency.

### **Education & Credentials**

Master of Science in Petroleum Data Management University of Aberdeen 2021

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science University of Lagos 1997

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

- PSM1 Professional Scrum Master (Scrum.org) (2023)
- CPDA Certified Petroleum Data Analyst (Professional Petroleum Data Management) (2021)
- CDMP Certified Data Management Professional Associate (DAMA International) (2020)
- ITP Information Technology Professional (Information and Communications Technology Council) (2019)
- PMP Project Management Professional (Project Management Institute) (2009)

#### SKILLS HIGHLIGHTS

**Software/Tools**: Python scripting, DBT, MS Power BI, Tableau, MS Project, Toad, Oracle SQL Plus, PL/SQL, SQL Developer, MS Excel, ServiceNow, MS Azure, SQL Server Management Studio, Visual Studio Code, Microsoft 365 Suite, SharePoint, JIRA

**Data Analysis**: Improving data quality; Data modeling; Metadata management; Data integration strategy; Enforcing data entitlement and obligations; Data security; Implementing data governance framework; Task automation

**Business Analysis:** Leading requirements gathering; Conducting stakeholder engagement; Developing business case; Embedding data/business processes; Developing policies, SOPs & training materials; Continuous process improvement; Managing changes; Release management

**Project Management:** Defining and controlling project; Staff training & development; Agile, waterfall methodology; Budget administration; Change management; Project setup and close-out; Resource management; Risk assessments

# **Professional Experience**

#### Data Architect, Ministry of Health, BC Public Service, BC (Jan 2024 – Date)

- Use a combination of technologies to build and maintain data and metadata ETL pipelines that support provisioning of data for health-related research projects
- Collaborate with stakeholders to improve data utility, data quality, metadata, data access, and systems functionality
- Use system engineering tools and methods such as data and process modeling, data normalization,
   functional decomposition, and data analysis to ensure integrity and continuity of ministry and health sector
- Monitor and solve data quality deficits, anomalies, and issues. Develops solutions to resolve source data problems and makes recommendations on functionality, upgrades, tuning, and configuration changes
- Experience in data modeling and/or data analysis techniques including record linkage (this includes demonstrated knowledge of relational database systems, data management principles, and/or structured analysis and design)
- Demonstrated experience using coding tools like SQL, R, and Python
- Collaborate with team in an agile environment using tools like Jira for task monitoring and Gitlab for code version control

#### Enterprise Architect, Ministry of Health, BC Public Service, BC (Dec 2023 – Oct 2024)

- Contributed to the development, definition, implementation, and enforcement of architecture policy, procedures, and standards.
- Provided technical expertise to systems professionals supporting corporate databases and applications.
- Collaborates in the development of multi-year technology and service roadmaps, plans and strategies.
- Analyzed and contributed to developing solutions, strategies, models, policies, standards, and best practices
  for topics including: Information management; Identity and identifier management; and IM/IT security and
  privacy architecture
- Contributed to management of the BC Health Enterprise Architecture Program, including but not limited to: planning and priority setting activities; EA repository management; committee secretariat services; architecture review board operations; program reporting; coordinating intake of work
- Highlight: Created and maintained artifacts, documents, and diagrams within the provincial enterprise architecture repository.

## Senior Data Analyst, Ministry of Social Development and Poverty Reduction, BC (May 2023 – Dec 2023)

- Developed efficient data products to satisfy data requests for various data initiatives using SQL queries, python and R scripts, MS PowerBI
- Designed and deployed reports and dashboards, to meet business needs and supports data-driven decision making
- Perform exploratory data analysis and research on ministry's data warehouse to identify data points that can support feasibility studies for various social programs
- <u>Highlight</u>: Developed data collection plan to guide program evaluation strategy for the BC Contact Centre program.

# Principal Technical Data Management Consultant, Shell Petroleum Development Company (November 2021 - July 2022)

- Accountable for functional and discipline leadership for over 20 technical data analysts across designated Shell Companies in Nigeria. Manage and resolve stakeholders' issues escalations and interdependencies.
- Supervised direct reports by setting quarterly and yearly appraisal targets, conducted performance reviews, delegated tasks, and managed absence-cover resource redeployments to achieve business outcomes
- Developed presentations for departmental leadership on detailed proposal for business process reengineering resulting in team transformation for improved effectiveness and better customer-focused service delivery
- Conducted investigations of operational or process issues and collaborated with other systems professionals to identify potential solutions while assessing external and internal risks and other impacts
- Defined, developed, implemented, and reviewed technical standard operating procedures, processes, and work instructions governing the performance of data management tasks.
- Reporting recommendations to executives on portfolios and individual project status.
- Monitored progress of regulatory data submission to in-country National Data Repository and directly
  engaged senior government officials to negotiate new approach and service management with defined
  Service Level Agreements
- <u>Highlight</u>: Developed the technical framework for the transfer of subsurface data and systems during the planned divestment of selected assets to protect Shell intellectual property (IP) and other commercially sensitive information (CSI)

#### Team Lead - East Asset Data Management, Brunei Shell Petroleum (November 2017 - November 2021)

- Coordinate procurement and setup of physical printers for petrophysical logs for multiple departments. Conducted requirement gathering and cost-benefit analysis. Collaborated with cross-functional teams and external vendors to identify any constraints.
- Fostered a productive team environment for team members with various disability management issues through proactive work assignments
- Developed business cases including feasibility studies, risk assessments, and cost-benefit analysis of solution alternatives. Performed benefits realization review on completed projects.
- Led planning and delivery of multiple functional improvement projects by defining scope and objectives, managing schedules, and resolving conflicts throughout the project life cycle
- Identify data governance and data quality improvement initiatives to support data-driven decision-making
- Prevented costly project rework by providing technical data management advice to over 100 engineers and data practitioners on standard operating procedures, policies, and processes
- Adept at using proprietary and industry-standard tools (MS PowerBI; python scripting) to automate manual activities and build dashboards for monitoring various team deliverables
- Contributed to company-wide employee well-being by facilitating Shell Health Resilience Boost sessions to a combined audience of more than 200 staff thereby showcasing excellent verbal communication skills
- Supervised 7-members team to provide operational support for asset team of up to 70 engineers
- <u>Highlight</u>: Led the development and presentation of training/educational materials for annual 3-day TDM Fundamentals course for over 65 new data managers and petroleum engineers; achieved cost savings of \$3500 per participant from January 2018 to November 2021

#### Senior Subsurface Data Consultant, Shell Petroleum Development Company (January 2010 - November 2017)

- Participated in the development, implementation, and review of standard operating procedures and work instructions for proper loading of data into corporate data stores to comply with data quality requirements
- Managed data delivery interfaces with the seismic processing team to safeguard all seismic products by documenting data lineage and all metadata that will aid future retrieval
- Collaborated with other facilitators to deliver training sessions on Introduction to Technical Data Management (TDM 101) for data managers and Petroleum Engineers
- Led multiple integration projects to align data between proprietary and industry-standard data stores to allow users map well data across multiple project stages
- Supervised the activities of other data managers and provided required training and coaching for on-the-job delivery
- Directed continuous process improvements to modernize project databases by configuring and deploying data synchronizations.
- Collaborated with stakeholders to build, test, and deploy customized solutions to resolve data integration issues.
- Contributed to employee well-being by presenting Shell Health Resilience Programme sessions; conducted more than four sessions over six months for 120 participants
- <u>Highlight:</u> Managed a multi-year project (with a budget of over USD800,000) to deploy R5000 Openworks and CDS systems across three Operating Units in two countries (SPDC and SNEPCO in Nigeria and SHLGB in Gabon)

#### Senior IT Project Manager (Subsurface), Shell Petroleum Development Company (October 2006 - December 2009)

- Managed data migration projects from legacy systems into new ones to preserve data integrity
- Managed data archiving and restore operations for various subsurface studies and projects through effective engagements of project teams and other stakeholders
- Learned cross-cultural team collaboration during a 3-months short-term assignment at Shell International Exploration and Production, Netherlands

#### Business/Application Support Analyst, Shell Petroleum Development Company (September 2001 - October 2006)

- Developed functional specifications for custom business systems and applications
- Developed and implemented communication plans, to ensure stakeholder requirements and priorities are gathered effectively
- Coordinated business continuity readiness for disaster recovery planning and operations.
- Provided business analysis support for teams by eliciting and documenting business requirements used for in-house application development projects
- Provided application portfolio management for custom and industry applications
- Used PL/SQL, HTML, and JavaScript to develop fully functional bespoke applications interfacing with Oracle or MS-SQL relational databases e.g. Conflict of Interest web application developed and deployed to over 4000 staff